It is the turbulent Sengoku period.
어지러운 전국 시대.
Warlords keep on fighting day and night over Jipangu State, where Karakuri people live.
카라쿠리인이 사는 지팡구국에서는 군웅할거하여 밤낮으로 접전이 계속되고
Karakuri martial artists were sharpening their swords, dreaming of victory and honor.
카라쿠리 무예가들도 승리와 영광을 꿈꾸며 맹렬히 싸우고 있었다.
And now, a wild hero has arrived, seeking to be the number one Karakuri martial artist!
그리고 지금, 카라쿠리 무예가 제일을 꿈꾸는 터무니없는 영웅이 탄생했다!
Musashi is here-dasu!
무사시 등장이오!
Karakuri Kengouden
카라쿠리 검호전: 무사시 로드
A man always dreams of the day
사내는 언제나 세계 한가운데서
in the center of the world to become
제일 강해질 날을
AH! AH! the strongest
아! 아! 꿈꿔라
Raise the sword of your heart high to the wide sky
마음의 칼을 넓은 하늘로 번쩍 쳐들어
Raise the curtain to the road of adventure
모험의 길의 막을 연다
A skilled swordsman roams on Jipangu State
지팡구국을 떠도는 검호
His name is Musashi, a Karakuri man
그 이름은 카라쿠리인 무사시
Go! Fight!
가라! 싸워라!
The sound of fierce duels
격렬한 승부의 소리는
makes life dazzling
눈부신 인생
Battles of yesterdays make you stronger today
싸웠던 어제보다도 오늘 강해진다
Martial Arts! Dual Blade Musashi
무예! 이도류 무사시
Tomorrow will be glorious
내일은 빛난다
The sound of fierce duels
격렬한 승부의 소리는
makes life dazzling
눈부신 인생
Fight the utmost with the stillness
싸우는 한껏 고요함과 함께
Martial Arts! Dual Blade Musashi
무예! 이도류 무사시
His eyes shined! Musashi!
미간이 반짝였다 무사시!!
Once being rough in the Miyamoto village in mountains, Musashi was punished
산속의 미야모토 마을에서 목검을 쳐들고 난폭하게 굴던 무사시는
by Takuan, but Otsuru rescued him and Musashi went to train himself.
타쿠안에게 처벌받게 되었지만 오츠루에게 구해져 수련의 길에 나섰다.
He met Kojirō who will become his rival of life,
그리고 평생의 라이벌이 될 코지로하고 만났지만
and he was completely defeated without mercy.
무참히 완패하고 만 무사시.
Dark clouds were in front of him.
그의 앞길에는 먹구름이 닥친 것이었다.
Training in Tears
눈물의 수행은 배가 고프오
This place is Okayamāna castle town.
이곳은 오카야마나 성시이다.
I've heard about this place, but I never thought this place would be so lively-dasu!
이야기는 들었지만 성시가 이렇게 활기찰 줄은 몰랐소!
What a beautiful kimono! I want to have Otsuru wear one-dasu!
이렇게 아름다운 기모노가 있다니, 오츠루 씨에게 입혀보고 싶소!
Otsuru!
오츠루 씨!
Everything here was rightfully surprising to country-bred Musashi.
시골뜨기 무사시에게 이곳의 모든 것은 놀랄 만한 것이었다.
Aren't these pomegranates from Matsukasi-dasu!?
마츠카시의 석류 아니오!
2 mons.
2문.
Pay the price!
돈을 내!
Price?
돈?
I hope you wouldn't say you don't know?
설마 모른다고는 안 하겠지?
I know what a price is-dasu.
돈 정도는 알고 있소.
Then pay the price!
그럼 돈을 내!
Why would I-dasu?
왜오!
This is for sale! It is obvious that you have to pay!
이건 파는 것이야! 그걸 먹었으면 돈을 내는 게 당연하지!
What's so funny?!
뭐가 웃기냐!
There are pomegranates everywhere in my Miyamoto village, and thus are free-dasu!
이런 석류, 내 미야모토 마을에는 어디에든 있고 무료라오!
Paying for such thing is something to laugh about-dasu!
돈을 낸다면 그것이야말로 웃긴 일 아니오!
Too bad for ya, but you are not at Miyamoto village! Now, give me the money or...
안타깝게도 여긴 미야모토 마을이 아니다! 자, 돈을 내라! 안 내면...
Thief!
도둑이다!
What?! Where are you, thief?!
뭐? 어디냐, 도둑!
I'm talking about you!
너 말이야!
Me?
나?
What do you mean, to call this Musashi who will be the number one martial artist of Jipangu a thief-dasu?!
지팡구 제일의 무예가가 될 이 무사시에게 도둑이라고 부르는 건 무슨 소리오!
Help me!
살려주세요!
That voice must be a scream from a girl!
저건 분명히 여자아이의 비명!
It is not manly to not go rescue her right now-dasu!
이곳에서 한시라도 지체한다면 사내의 자격이 없소!
Mister! Consider yourself lucky to have your head intact-dasu!
아저씨! 넌 목이 계속 붙어있는 게 운이 좋소!
That's a relief-dasu...
다행이오...
Hey! You still gotta pay!
아! 돈!
The one surrounded by martial artists was a girl resembling Nishida Hikaru.
여러 명의 무예가에게 둘러싸여 있던 건 니시다 히카루하고 닮은 여자아이였다.
Miss, would you like to have a tea?
누나, 차 안 마실래?
Have a glass.
한잔 하는건 어때?
How about a drive on my wagon?
이 몸의 마차로 드라이브는 어때?
Please stop!
그만해 주세요!
Sis!
누나!
Who was that?!
누, 누구냐!
What the?
뭐야?
Who are you?!
뭐, 뭐냐, 네놈은!
The future number one martial artist of Jipangu!
지팡구 제일의 무예가가 될!
From Miyamaoto village,
미야모토 마을의
I am Musashi-dasu!
무사시라고 하오!
Aren't you interesting?
이 녀석!
You might get hurt!
다쳐도 모른다!
You're going to be hurt-dasu!
다치는 건 그쪽이오!
Thanks! Thank you! Thank you so much-dasu!
감사하오! 감사하오! 정말 고맙소!
Those martial artists are from Yoshioka Dōjō.
그 무예가들은 요시오카 도장의 사람들입니다.
Yoshioka Dōjō?
요시오카 도장?
Yes. It's a Dōjō in Miyako with the strongest martial artists in Jipangu.
네. 미야코에 있는 지팡구에서 제일 강한 무예가들이 모인 도장입니다.
(Miyako: the capital)
(미야코: 도읍지)
Strongest in Jipangu?
지팡구에서 제일 강하다고 하셨소?
A branch has opened recently at this castle town.
그 지부가 최근 이 성시에 생겼답니다. 요시오카 일문이라는 것만으로 모두가 벌벌 떨 뿐이니...
They act as if everything is theirs.
뭐든 제 것인 양 행동하고...
But as long as Musashi's here, no need to fear-dasu!
그래도 이 무사시가 있는 한 더 이상 무서워 할 필요 없소!
Don't let your guards down. Your opponent were mere beginners; there are lots of strong people!
그래도 조심해요. 아까는 초보들 뿐. 더 강한 자들이 가득 있답니다!
No need to worry! Until now, I only lost a battle once-dasu!
에이, 괜찮소! 지금까지 나, 단 한번밖에 진 적이 없소!
Musashi really sounds like a name that I can depend on!
무사시 씨라면 정말 믿고 맡겨도 될 것 같은 분이네요!
You can eat this! These are be the best dangos you will ever have.
자, 드세요! 맛 한번 끝내주는 단고에요.
Whoa, these dangos really look tasty-dasu!
우와, 맛있어 보이는 단고이오!
Thank you for the meal!
잘 먹겠소!
That dish!
그 요리!
Will you be able to eat it alive?
과연 살아서 먹을 수 있을까.
Sējūrō
세주로
Hey, you. Tell your name.
어이, 거기. 뭐라 부르면 되나.
Tell me your name first if you want to know-dasu.
알고 싶으면 먼저 이름을 대시오.
What did you say?!
뭐라고?!
I am Yoshioka. Yoshioka Sējūrō!
난 요시오카. 요시오카 세주로!
Yoshioka Sējūrō!
요시오카 세주로!
He is our master who is a son of the master of Yoshioka clan from Miyako!
수도에서 오신 요시오카 가문의 대선생의 자제분으로 우리들의 스승이시다!
He took the trouble for the first time ever since the Yoshioka Dōjō branch here opened to issue a warning from himself!
요시오카 도장 지부가 여기 오카야마나에 문을 연 이후 처음으로 특별히 경고하러 오셨다!
I am Musashi from Miyamoto village-dasu.
난 미야모토 마을의 무사시라고 하오.
So what's your business-dasu?
그래서 용건이 무엇이오?
I heard that our young students were attacked, so I came to show how things will work around here.
우리 젊은이가 불쌍하게 당했다고 하서 본보기를 보여주러 왔다.
Huh? That's a honor.
예? 음... 나 말이오?
So what's your payment-dasu?
그래서 뭘 주실 거오?
Manju?
만주?
Red bean paste?
물양갱?
Castella?
카스텔라?
This!
이거다!
My wooden sword...
목검이...
Damn you! Damn you! Damn you! Damn you!
이자식! 이자식! 이자식! 이자식! 이자식! 이자식!
That's a back side of my sword.
칼등이다.
That's our master Sējūrō!
역시 세주로 님!
Musashi!
무사시!
Hmph. He wasted my time with his mouth.
흥. 입만 큰 녀석.
Thus there is no way to let him live.
그러나 이런 자는 살려둘 방법이 없군.
A man like this should disappear for the world as soon as possible.
세상을 위해서는 이런 자는 빨리 사라지는 게 낫다.
Prepare yourself!
각오해라!
How refreshing!
시원하다!
How dare you!
네이놈, 어디서 감히!
Bokuden
보쿠덴
Oh my, if you get all heated up, you'll end up making all that pee evaporate.
이런, 그렇게 열을 내면 모처럼의 오줌이 증발해.
How dare... You're going down first! Get down here!
이게... 네놈부터 쓰러트려주마! 내려와라!
Look out!
위험해!
Wha... what the?!
뭐, 뭐야?!
Damn!
젠장!
How's that? Should I take my sword out, you will not stand a chance.
어떻냐, 칼을 빼잡는 순간 너는 이 몸에게 한 방이란다.
Mutōdori!
무토도리!
(Mutōdori: 無刀取り. Defeating opponent with sword without using one)
(무토도리: 無刀取り. 자신은 칼을 들지 않고 칼을 든 상대를 이김)
You should take a short nap too.
너도 잠깐 여기서 자고 있어라.
That was a nice stretch to wake me up. Thank you for the service.
졸린 참에 가볍게 운동을 했군. 이것 참, 고맙구만.
W- wait for a moment. You seem to be a famed martial artist...
자, 잠깐 기다리시오. 필시 이름 있는 무예가라고 보인다만...
Nah, I'm just a plain old guy.
무슨, 단지 늙은이일 뿐이다.
Name, at least...
하다못해 존함이라도...
Bokuden.
보쿠덴이다.
The one to be called a master swordsman, Tsukahara Bokuden!
검성이라는 평을 받던 츠카하라 보쿠덴!
I sincerely apologize!
실례했습니다!
He's that Tsukahara Bokuden! It looks like he's full of weak points, but he got none!
저 사람이 츠카하라 보쿠덴! 허점 가득해 보였는데 어디에도 허점이 없어!
Bokuden...
보쿠덴...
Musashi, are you hurt?
무사시 님, 상처는?
Musashi!
무사시 님!
Where do you think you're going by following Bokuden, Musashi? Wait for the stormy latter half!
보쿠덴을 따라가 어디에 갈 것이냐, 무사시! 질풍노도의 후반을 기다려라!
Please wait!
기다려 주시오!
Hey there! Can't you hear me asking you to stop-dasu?
거기! 기다리라는 말이 안 들리시오!
That's it!
그래!
You've dropped your money!
돈을 떨어뜨렸소!
Wait, what?
어, 뭐?
Please accept me as your student-dasu!
절 제자로 받아들여 주시오!
If you give me back the money I dropped, I'll take you as a student... not.
떨어뜨린 돈을 돌려주는 대신 제자로 삼는다니 말도 안 된다.
What?
뭐라?
Stop! Bakaden!
멈춰라, 바보쿠덴!
Hey, now! I am Bokuden!
이 녀석! 난 보쿠덴이다!
Take me as your student!
날 제자로 해라!
Raising students isn't my thing.
난 제자 키우는 주의가 아니라 말이지.
My thing is to be a student-dasu!
난 제자 되는 주의이오!
Make... me... your... student...
날... 제자로... 날... 제자로...
Following Bokuden for 3,000 ris,
보쿠덴을 따라 삼만리,
well, not that much, but anyway, Musashi stubbornly kept following.
까진 아니어도, 무사시는 끈질기게 따라갔다.
I did it...
해냈다...
Please!
부탁이오!
Once decided, stake my life. It is the way of Musashi-dasu!
한번 결심하면 목숨을 거는 것, 이것이 무사시의 방법이오!
Hey! What's wrong? Wake up!
어이! 왜 그러냐! 정신 차려라!
Another dish!
한 그릇 더!
I beg of you-dasu!
부탁이오!
Everything you've done considered, I don't really have a choice, do I? I will take you a student.
그렇게까지 굴면 어쩔 수 없지. 제자로 해 주겠다.
But! The training will be painful!
그 대신! 수련은 쓰라릴 것이다.
Aren't all trainings painful?
쓰라리니까 수련이잖소?
Huh? Well, I guess.
어? 뭐, 그렇지.
To become the number one martial artist of Jipangu,
지팡구 제일의 무예가가 되기 위해서라면 불 속이든 물 속이든 어디든 어떤 쓰라린 수련이라도 받아 보이겠소!
Got it? No matter what kind of opponent is, I'll hit him hard and make him fly... over the cloud-dasu.
알겠소? 어떤 어려운 상대라도 구름 머얼리... 날려 주겠소.
What a strange guy.
참 이상한 녀석이군.
Musashi! You're a student of Tsukahara Bokuden now?
무사시! 츠카하라 보쿠덴의 제자가 되었냐!
I pray for you to open your eyes and become a good rival of mine.
눈이 뜨여 좋은 라이벌이 되어 주기를 바란다.
Keep your waist straight!
허리에 힘이 없다! 허리에!
The most important thing when yielding a sword is to use your waist to cleave!
검을 다룰 때 제일 중요한 것은 허리로 베는 것이다!
Got it!
예!
Do you understand, Musashi?
알겠느냐, 무사시?
Body training is what it is!
단련은 단련!
Mental training will raise your guts.
담련은 즉 담력.
Gut means the spiritual strength of not getting perplexed no matter what.
담력은 어떤 일이 있어도 당황하지 않는 강한 정신력을 말한다.
To raise your guts, you must understand the nature and train your skills.
그 담력을 훈련하기 위해서는 자연과 기술을 단련하는 것이다.
Got it!
예!
To defeat an opponent, your feet must be as quick as your sword!
상대에게 이기기 위해서는 발도 빨라지지 않으면 안 된다!
Sometimes to run away is to win!
가끔은 달아나는 게 이기는 것일 때도 있다!
Got it!
예!
Of course your body also has to become strong.
몸도 당연 강해지지 않으면 안 된다.
Ten years early, I see.
10년은 이르군.
Focus, Musashi. The most essential elements of real-life training are
알았냐, 무사시. 현실 수련에서 가장 중요한 것은
"Sight" first, "foot" second, "guts" third, and "force" fourth.
첫째, "안", 둘째, "족", 셋째, "담", 넷째, "력"이다.
You've already learned "force", "guts", and "foot".
이 력과 담과 족은 이미 배웠지.
"Sight" here means to see. To see your opponent.
이 "안"이라는 것은 보는 걸 말한다. 한마디로 말하자면 상대를 보는 것.
There are two kinds of sight: sight of eyes, and sight of swords.
여기에는 "안의 눈"과 "검의 눈"이라는 게 있다.
Sight of eye means intuition; sight of sword means to observe the phenomenon of objects.
"안"의 눈은 직감, "검"의 눈은 사물의 현상을 보는 것이다.
I'm teaching you even using my dinner time and you're...
이 녀석아, 내가 기껏 먹을 시간까지 아껴가며 가르쳐주고 있는데...
You even ate my dinner!
내 밥까지 먹었구나...
I did it!
해, 해냈다!
Good job, Musashi. From today we will go to the second step.
휼륭하다, 무사시. 오늘부터는 제 2단계로 나아가겠다.
Thank you!
예!
What's bothering you, Otsuru?
왜 그러냐, 오츠루.
Master... I have something I must apologize.
아, 스님... 저, 사과해야만 하는 것이...
About letting Musashi run away?
무사시를 달아나게 둔 것 말이냐?
Yes.
네.
Don't worry. You did a good job, Otsuru.
아니다, 잘 말해 주었다, 오츠루.
I was thinking that it was time to let him go anyway.
사실 슬슬 놔주어도 될 것이라고 생각하던 참이었다.
I could have forgiven him, but your compassion serves better as an everlasting lesson for him.
그러나 내가 용서해 자유롭게 풀어주는 것보다도 네가 녀석을 배려해 주는 마음이 더욱 평생 잊지 못할 교훈을 남겨 줬을 게야.
Everything will turn out well for Musashi!
뭐든 무사시를 위해서 잘 될 테다!
I wonder what's Musashi doing at where.
무사시 녀석, 지금쯤 어디서 뭘 하고 있으려나.
But no need to worry at all!
뭐, 그래도 어떻게든 걱정할 필요는 없다!
He's Musashi after all. He'll bravely fight for his future.
무사시니까. 씩씩하게 뭐든 해낼 테니까!
Soft and naive!
무디다! 무뎌!
Master!
스승님!
What are you doing-dasu?!
뭔 짓이오!
You idiot! Do you think your opponent is going to save you in real battles?
바보 녀석! 실제 싸움에서 구해주는 놈이 있을 거라 생각하나!
Musashi!
무사시 씨!
Musashi! Get a grip! Do you want to die at such a place?
무사시 씨! 정신 차려요! 이런 곳에서 죽어도 괜찮아요?
Otsuru.
오츠루 씨.
Musashi! To drop dead at such a place, you truly were a waste of time!
무사시! 이런 곳에서 뻗다니 말할 가치도 없는 놈이구나!
Idiot.
바보 녀석.
Kojirō!
코지로!
He was a fine guy, to keep onto his sword to his death.
괜찮은 사내었다... 죽을 때까지 검을 놓지 않다니.
Chink in the armor!
빈틈이오!
Good job, Musashi.
잘 했다, 무사시.
Excuse me!
실례했습니다!
Musashi, it's time for you to leave.
무사시, 너도 하산할 때가 온 듯 하구나.
Winds of era is calling me.
시대의 풍운이 날 부른다.
Musashi! You shall go to Miyako!
무사시! 넌 미야코에 가라!
To Miyako?
미야코에?
I have nothing more to teach. I taught everything I know to you.
네게는 더 이상 가르칠 게 없다. 내가 가진 모든 것을 가르쳤단 게다.
For the rest, Musashi, you shall hone yourself with your own hands!
나머지는 무사시, 네가 네 손으로 직접 닦아 나가야 한다.
Can you do it, Musashi?
할 수 있겠나, 무사시?
Yes!
예!
Musashi! First, become the number one martial artist of Jipangu!
무사시! 우선 지팡구 제일의 무예가가 되어라!
Thank you!
감사합니다!
Lastly, do not forget the ultimate purpose of a sword!
마지막으로 검의 궁극의 목적은 단 하나!
To win without fighting.
싸우지 않고 이기는 것.
Go, Musashi! For the future of Jipangu!
가라, 무사시! 미래의 지팡구를 위해서!
Got it!
예!
It will be a problem if I get tired over my limits.
이 이상 무리하면 견딜 수가 없겠군.
Still, he was an interesting guy with good guts.
그래도 녀석, 꽤 근성있고 재미있는 녀석이었어.
With a high ambition, he heads to Miyako! What will be waiting for him? A flower, or a storm?
청운의 뜻을 품고 미야코에, 미야코에! 그 무사시의 앞길을 기다리는 것은 꽃인가, 폭풍인가!
That does not matter! Go forward, Musashi! Dive into flowers and storms! That's the path of swordsmanship of a man.
그러나! 무사시여, 가라! 꽃에도 폭풍에도 뛰어들어라! 그것이야말로 검을 잡은 사내의 길.
Sometimes the moon jumps over
허공의 주머니에 달이
the pocket of empty sky
뛰어넘어가는 일도 있어
Laugh loudly and
큰 소리로 웃으면
morning will come tomorrow
내일에는 아침이 와
Don't worry too much about losing
잃는 것 따위는 아무것도 아니야
Keep going! Go for it!
계속 해나가! 앞으로 가!
A bare hand is strong
맨손은 강해
That's how it is! Let's go lightly
그런 거야! 가볍게 가자
That's how life is! Look, a chance
인생 그런 거야! 기회가 어라,
follows us wagging its tail!
꼬리를 흔들며 쫒아와!
That's how it is! Let's go lightly
그런 거야! 가볍게 가자
That's how the future is, too! Look, tomorrow
미래도 그런 거야! 내일이 어라,
is opening its hands and smiling at us!
양손을 벌리고 웃고 있어!
After a harsh training, I became stronger and now I'm heading for the Miyako Palace-dasu.
혹독한 수련 후에, 한층 강해진 나는 미야코 팔레스에 향하오.
Wow, it sure is a big city, and there sure are lots of weird guys-dasu!
이야, 역시나 대도시, 이상한 녀석이 많소!
In front of a giant fighter whose hobby is collecting thousands swords, some child-looking guy appears.
칼을 천 개 모으는 것이 취미라는 거대한 괴승 앞에 나타난 것은, 어린아이 같은 용모의 누군가.
Next episode: Benkei at the Capital Castle City-dasu.
다음 이야기! 수도의 고조의 벤케이오
It will pierce through your eyes-dasu!
네 눈동자를 뚫고 갈 것이오!
Next Episode
다음 이야기
Benkei at the Capital Castle City
미야코 고조의 벤케이오
Look forwards for it!
기대하세요!